<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-dots-home-network-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DOTS signal Call Home">Denial-of-Service Open Threat
    Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel Call Home</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joshi Harsha" initials="J." surname="Harsha">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>harsha_joshi@mcafee.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jon Shallow" initials="J." surname="Shallow">
      <organization>NCC Group</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <code></code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>supjps-ietf@jpshallow.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>DOTS</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document presents DOTS signal channel Call Home service, which
      enables a DOTS server to initiate a secure connection to a DOTS client,
      and to receive the attack traffic information from the DOTS client. The
      DOTS server in turn uses the attack traffic information to identify the
      compromised devices launching the outgoing DDOS attack and takes
      appropriate mitigation action.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <section anchor="problem" title="The Problem">
        <t>The DOTS signal channel protocol <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> is used to carry
        information about a network resource or a network (or a part thereof)
        that is under a Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS) attack. Such
        information is sent by a DOTS client to one or multiple DOTS servers
        so that appropriate mitigation actions are undertaken on traffic
        deemed suspicious. Various use cases are discussed in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases"></xref>.</t>

        <t>IoT devices are becoming more and more prevalent in home networks,
        and with compute and memory becoming cheaper and cheaper, various
        types of IoT devices are available in the consumer market at
        affordable price. But on the downside, the main threat being most of
        these IoT devices are bought off-the-shelf and most manufacturers
        haven't considered security in the product design. IoT devices
        deployed in home networks can be easily compromised, they do not have
        easy mechanism to upgrade, and IoT manufactures may cease manufacture
        and/or discontinue patching vulnerabilities on IoT devices. However,
        these vulnerable and compromised devices will continue be used for a
        long period of time in the home, and the end-user does not know that
        IoT devices in his/her home are compromised. The compromised IoT
        devices are typically used for launching DDoS attacks on the victim
        while the owner/administrator of the home network is not aware about
        such misbehaviors. Similar to other DDoS attack, the victim in this
        attack can be an application server, a host, a router, a firewall, or
        an entire network.</t>

        <t>Nowadays, network devices in a home network offer network security,
        for instance, firewall/IPS service on a home router or gateway to
        protect the devices connected to the home network from external and
        internal attacks. Over the years several techniques have been
        identified to detect DDoS attacks, some of these techniques can be
        enabled on home network devices but most of them are used in the
        Internet Service Provider (ISP)'s network. The ISP offering DDoS
        mitigation service can detect outgoing DDoS attack traffic originating
        from its subscribers or the ISP may receive filtering rules (for
        example, using BGP flowspec <xref target="RFC5575"></xref>) from
        downstream service provider to filter, block, or rate-limit DDoS
        attack traffic originating from the ISP's subscribers to the
        downstream target.</t>

        <t>Some of the DDoS attacks like spoofed RST or FIN packets,
        Slowloris, and TLS re-negotiation are difficult to detect on the home
        network devices without adversely affecting its performance. The
        reason is typically home routers have fast path to boost the
        throughput. For every new TCP/UDP flow, only the first few packets are
        punted through the slow path. Hence, it is not possible to detect
        various DDoS attacks in the slow path, since the attack payload is
        sent to the target server after the flow is switched to fast path.
        Deep packet inspection (DPI) of all the packets of a flow would be
        able to detect some of the attacks. However, a full-fledged DPI to
        detect these type of DDoS attacks is functionally or operationally not
        possible for all the devices attached to the home network owing to the
        memory and CPU limitations of the home routers. Further, for certain
        DDoS attacks the ability to distinguish legitimate traffic from
        attacker traffic on a per packet basis is complex. This complexity
        originates from the fact that the packet itself may look "legitimate"
        and no attack signature can be identified. The anomaly can be
        identified only after detailed statistical analysis.</t>

        <t>The ISP on the other hand can detect the DDoS attack originating
        from a home network, but the ISP does not have a mechanism to detect
        which device in the home network is generating the DDoS attack
        traffic. The primary reason being that devices in a IPv4 Home network
        are typically behind a NAT border. Even in case of a IPv6 Home
        network, although the ISP can identify the infected device in the Home
        network launching the DDoS traffic by tracking its unique IPv6
        address, the infected device can easily change the IP address to evade
        remediation.</t>

        <t>Existing approaches are still suffering from misused access network
        resources by abusing devices; the support of means for blocking such
        attacks close to the sources are missing. In particular, the DOTS
        signal protocol do not discuss cooperative DDoS mitigation between the
        home network and ISP to the suppress the outbound DDoS attack traffic
        originating from the home network.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The Solution">
        <t>This specification addresses the problems discussed in <xref
        target="problem"></xref> and presents DOTS signal channel Call Home
        extension, which enables the DOTS server to initiate a secure
        connection to the DOTS client, and the DOTS client then conveys the
        attack traffic information to the DOTS server. The DOTS server uses
        the DDoS attack traffic information to identify the compromised device
        in its domain launching the DDoS attack, notifies the network
        administrator, and takes appropriate mitigation action. The mitigation
        action can be to quarantine the compromised device or block its
        traffic to the attack target until the mitigation request is
        withdrawn.</t>

        <t>For instance, the DOTS server in the home network initiates the
        Call Home during peace time and then subsequently the DOTS client in
        the ISP environment can initiate mitigation requests whenever the ISP
        detects there is an attack from a compromised device in the DOTS
        server's domain.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions and Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>The reader should be familiar with the terms defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DOTS Signal Channel Call Home">
      <section title="Procedure">
        <t>DOTS signal channel Call Home preserves all but one of the DOTS
        client/server roles in the DOTS protocol stack, as compared to DOTS
        client-initiated DOTS signal channel protocol. The one and only role
        reversal that occurs are at the TCP/TLS or DTLS layers; that is, the
        DOTS server acts as a DTLS client and the DOTS client acts as a DTLS
        server or the DOTS server acts as a TCP/TLS client and the DOTS client
        acts as a TCP/TLS server. The DOTS server initiates TCP/TLS handshake
        or DTLS handshake to the DOTS client.</t>

        <t>For example, a home network element (e.g., home router) co-located
        with a DOTS server (likely, a client-domain DOTS gateway) is the
        TCP/TLS server and DTLS server. However, when calling home, the DOTS
        server initially assumes the role of the TCP/TLS client and DTLS
        client, but the network element's role as a DOTS server remains the
        same. Further, existing certificate chains and mutual authentication
        mechanisms between the DOTS agents are unaffected by Call Home
        function. This Call Home function enables the DOTS server co-located
        with a network element (possibly behind NATs and firewalls) reachable
        by only the intended DOTS client and hence the DOTS server cannot be
        subjected to DDoS attacks. Other motivations for introducing Call Home
        are discussed in Section 1.1 of <xref target="RFC8071"></xref>.</t>

        <t><xref target="signalch"></xref> illustrates sample Call Home flow
        exchange:</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="signalch"
            title="DOTS Signal Channel Call Home Sequence Diagram">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                DOTS                                DOTS 
               Server                              Client
                 |                                    |
                 |         1. (D)TLS connection       |
                 |----------------------------------->|
                 |         2. Mitigation request      |
                 |<-----------------------------------|
                 |                                    |
]]></artwork>
          </figure>This diagram makes the following points:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>If UDP transport is used, the DOTS server begins by initiating
            a DTLS connection to the DOTS client. The DOTS client MUST support
            accepting DTLS connection on the IANA-assigned port defined in
            <xref target="port"></xref>, but MAY be configured to listen to a
            different port. If TCP is used, the DOTS server begins by
            initiating a TCP connection to the DOTS client. The DOTS client
            MUST support accepting TCP connections on the IANA-assigned port
            defined in <xref target="port"></xref>, but MAY be configured to
            listen to a different port. Using this TCP connection, the DOTS
            server initiates an TLS connection to the DOTS client. The happy
            eyeballs mechanism explained in Section 4.3 of <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> can be used for
            initiation of both TCP and UDP sessions.</t>

            <t>Using this (D)TLS connection, the DOTS client requests,
            withdraws, or retrieves the status of mitigation requests.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="DOTS Signal Channel Extension">
        <section title="Mitigation Request">
          <t>This specification extends the mitigation request defined in
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> to convey the
          attacker source prefixes and source port numbers. The DOTS client in
          the mitigation request conveys the following new parameters in the
          CBOR body of the mitigation request:<list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="source-prefix:">A list of attacker prefixes used to
              attack the target. Prefixes are represented using Classless
              Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR) notation <xref
              target="RFC4632"></xref>. <vspace blankLines="0" />As a
              reminder, the prefix length MUST be less than or equal to 32
              (resp. 128) for IPv4 (resp. IPv6).<vspace blankLines="1" />The
              prefix list MUST NOT include broadcast, loopback, or multicast
              addresses. These addresses are considered as invalid values. In
              addition, the DOTS client MUST validate that attacker prefixes
              are within the scope of the DOTS server's domain.<vspace
              blankLines="1" />This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="source-port-range:">A list of port numbers used by
              the attack traffic flows. <vspace blankLines="1" />A port range
              is defined by two bounds, a lower port number (lower-port) and
              an upper port number (upper-port). When only 'lower-port' is
              present, it represents a single port number. <vspace
              blankLines="1" />For TCP, UDP, Stream Control Transmission
              Protocol (SCTP) <xref target="RFC4960"></xref>, or Datagram
              Congestion Control Protocol (DCCP) <xref
              target="RFC4340"></xref>, a range of ports can be, for example,
              0-1023, 1024-65535, or 1024-49151. <vspace blankLines="1" />This
              is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="source-icmp-type:">A list of ICMP types used by the
              attack traffic flows. An ICMP type range is defined by two
              bounds, a lower ICMP type (lower-type) and an upper ICMP type
              (upper-type). When only 'lower-type' is present, it represents a
              single ICMP type. <vspace blankLines="1" />This is an optional
              attribute.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The 'source-prefix' parameter is a mandatory attribute when the
          attack traffic information is signaled by the DOTS client in the
          call home scenario. The 'target-uri' or 'target-fqdn' parameters can
          be included in the mitigation request for diagnostic purpose to
          notify the DOTS server domain administrator, but SHOULD NOT be used
          to determine the target IP addresses. Because <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> requires
          'target-prefix', 'target-fqdn','target-uri', or 'alias-name' to be
          present in a PUT request, and given the recommendation on target IP
          addresses, 'target-prefix' must be present in a call home request.
          </t>

          <t>When a translator is on-path, the DOTS server uses the attack
          traffic information to find the internal source IP address (or
          internal source port numbers, if needed) of the compromised device
          and blocks the traffic from the compromised device traffic to the
          attack target. Triggers for the withdrawal of the corresponding
          filters are policy-based, for example, filters may be permanent or
          be removed when the mitigation request is withdrawn. The DOTS server
          domain administrator consent MAY be required to block the traffic
          from the compromised device to the attack target. An implementation
          MAY have a configuration knob to block the traffic from the
          compromised device to the attack target with or without DOTS server
          domain administrator consent. If the attack traffic is blocked, the
          DOTS server informs the DOTS client that the attack is being
          mitigated.</t>

          <t>If the attack traffic information is identified by the DOTS
          server or the DOTS server domain administrator as legitimate
          traffic, the mitigation request is rejected, and 4.09 (Conflict) is
          returned to the DOTS client. The conflict-clause (defined in Section
          4.4.1 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref>)
          indicates the cause of the conflict. The following new value is
          defined:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="4:">Mitigation request rejected. This code is
              returned by the DOTS server to indicate the attack traffic has
              been classified as legitimate traffic.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>If the DOTS server is co-located with a home router, it can
          program the packet processor to punt all the traffic from the
          compromised device to the target to slow path. The home router
          inspects the punted slow path traffic to detect and block the
          outgoing DDoS attack traffic or quarantine the device (e.g., using
          MAC level filtering) until it is remediated, and notifies the home
          administrator about the compromised device.</t>

          <t>TBD:</t>

          <t>a) Do we also want to convey Attack Name/type or ID (the home
          router may not be capable of detecting new emerging/sophisticated
          attacks) ?</t>

          <t>b) Is DOTS data channel Call Home service required (if required,
          can RESTCONF Call Home defined in RFC8071 be used) ?</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="YANG" title="DOTS Signal Call Home YANG Module ">
          <section title="Mitigation Request Tree Structure">
            <t>This document augments the "dots-signal-channel" DOTS signal
            YANG module defined in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> for signaling the
            attack traffic information. This document defines the YANG module
            "ietf-dots-signal-call-home", which has the following tree
            structure:<figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[module: ietf-dots-signal-call-home
  augment /ietf-signal:dots-signal/ietf-signal:message-type
          /ietf-signal:mitigation-scope/ietf-signal:scope:
    +--rw source-prefix*            inet:ip-prefix {source-signaling}?
    +--rw source-port-range* [lower-port upper-port] {source-signaling}?
    |  +--rw lower-port    inet:port-number
    |  +--rw upper-port    inet:port-number
    +--rw source-icmp-type-range* [lower-type upper-type] {source-signaling}?
       +--rw lower-type    uint8
       +--rw upper-type    uint8

]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Call Home Mitigation Request YANG Module ">
            <t><figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-dots-signal-call-home@2018-09-28.yang"

module ietf-dots-signal-call-home {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-call-home";
  prefix signal-call-home;

  import ietf-inet-types {
    prefix inet;
    reference
      "Section 4 of RFC 6991";
  }
  import ietf-dots-signal-channel {
    prefix ietf-signal;
    reference
      "RFC XXXX: Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat
                 Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel Specification";
  }

  organization
    "IETF DDoS Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/dots/>
     WG List:  <mailto:dots@ietf.org>
     
     Editor:  Konda, Tirumaleswar Reddy
              <mailto:TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com>;

     Editor:  Mohamed Boucadair
              <mailto:mohamed.boucadair@orange.com>;

     Editor:  Jon Shallow
                 <mailto:jon.shallow@nccgroup.com>";
     
  description
    "This module contains YANG definition for the signaling
     messages exchanged between a DOTS client and a DOTS server
     for the call home deployment scenario.
     
     Copyright (c) 2018 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.
     
     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
     to the license terms contained in, the Simplified BSD License
     set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).
     
     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
     the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

  revision 2018-09-28 {
    description
      "Initial revision.";
    reference
      "RFC XXXX: Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat
                 Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel Call Home";
  }

  feature source-signaling {
    description
      "This feature means that source-related information
       can be supplied in mitigation requests.";
  }

  augment "/ietf-signal:dots-signal/ietf-signal:message-type/" + 
          "ietf-signal:mitigation-scope/ietf-signal:scope" {
    if-feature source-signaling;
    description "Attacker source details";

    leaf-list source-prefix {
      type inet:ip-prefix;
      description
        "IPv4 or IPv6 prefix identifying the attacker(s).";
    }
    list source-port-range {
      key "lower-port upper-port";
      description
        "Port range. When only lower-port is
         present, it represents a single port number.";
      leaf lower-port {
        type inet:port-number;
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Lower port number of the port range.";
      }
      leaf upper-port {
        type inet:port-number;
        must ". >= ../lower-port" {
           error-message
             "The upper port number must be greater than
              or equal to lower port number.";
        }
        description
          "Upper port number of the port range.";
      }
    }
    list source-icmp-type-range {
      key "lower-type upper-type";
      description
        "ICMP type range. When only lower-type is
         present, it represents a single ICMP type.";
      leaf lower-type {
        type uint8;
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Lower ICMP type of the ICMP type range.";
      }
      leaf upper-type {
        type uint8;
        must ". >= ../lower-type" {
           error-message
             "The upper ICMP type must be greater than
             or equal to lower ICMP type.";
        }
        description
          "Upper type of the ICMP type range.";
      }
    }
  }
}
<CODE ENDS>]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section anchor="port"
               title="DOTS Signal Channel Call Home UDP and TCP Port Number">
        <t>IANA is requested to assign the port number TBD to the DOTS signal
        channel Call Home protocol for both UDP and TCP from the "Service Name
        and Transport Protocol Port Number Registry" available at:
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/service-names-port-numbers/service-names-port-numbers.xhtml.</t>

        <t>The assignment of port number 4647 is strongly suggested (DOTS
        signal channel uses port number 4646).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="map" title="DOTS Signal Channel CBOR Mappings Registry">
        <t>This specification registers the 'source-prefix' and
        'source-port-range' parameters in the IANA "DOTS Signal Channel CBOR
        Mappings" registry established by <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The 'source-prefix' and 'source-port-range' are
        comprehension-optional parameters.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[+---------------------------+-------------+---------+---------------+--------+
| Parameter Name            | YANG        | CBOR    | CBOR Major    | JSON   |
|                           | Type        | Key     |    Type &     | Type   |
|                           |             |         | Information   |        |
+---------------------------+-------------+---------+---------------+--------+
| source-prefix             | leaf-list   |   0x8000| 4 array       | Array  |
|                           | inet:       |   (TBD) |               |        |
|                           |  ip-prefix  |         | 3 text string | String |
| source-port-range         | list        |   0x8001| 4 array       | Array  |
|                           |             |   (TBD) |               |        | 
| source-icmp-type-range    | list        |   0x8002| 4 array       | Array  |
|                           |             |   (TBD) |               |        |
| lower-type                | uint8       |   0x8003| 0 unsigned    | Number |
|                           |             |   (TBD) |               |        |
| upper-type                | uint8       |   0x8004| 0 unsigned    | Number |
|                           |             |   (TBD) |               |        |
+---------------------------+-------------+---------+---------------+--------+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="New DOTS Conflict Cause">
        <t>This document requests IANA to assign a new code from the "DOTS
        Conflict Cause Codes" registry:</t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol>Code</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Label</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>4</c>

          <c>request-rejected</c>

          <c>Mitigation request rejected. This code is returned by the DOTS
          server to indicate the attack traffic has been classified as
          legitimate traffic.</c>

          <c>[ThisDoc]</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="yang" title="DOTS Signal Channel YANG Module">
        <t>This document requests IANA to register the following URIs in the
        "IETF XML Registry" <xref target="RFC3688"></xref>: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[         URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-call-home
         Registrant Contact: The IESG.
         XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.

]]></artwork>
          </figure> This document requests IANA to register the following YANG
        modules in the "YANG Module Names" registry <xref
        target="RFC7950"></xref>.<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[         name: ietf-signal-call-home
         namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-call-home
         prefix: signal-call-home
         reference: RFC XXXX

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document deviates from standard DOTS signal channel usage by
      having the DOTS server initiate the TCP/TLS or DTLS connection. DOTS
      signal channel related security considerations discussed in Section 10
      of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> MUST be
      considered. DOTS agents MUST authenticate each other using (D)TLS before
      a DOTS signal channel session is considered valid.</t>

      <t>An attacker may launch a DoS attack on the DOTS client by having it
      perform computationally expensive operations, before deducing that the
      attacker doesn't possess a valid key. For instance, in TLS 1.3 <xref
      target="RFC8446"></xref>, the ServerHello message contains a Key Share
      value based on an expensive asymmetric key operation for key
      establishment. Common precautions mitigating DoS attacks are
      recommended, such as temporarily blacklisting the source address after a
      set number of unsuccessful authentication attempts.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBC.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7252"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7950"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3688"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8446"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4732"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7049"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4632"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8071"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4960"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4340"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5575"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
